Foreword by Jake Klamka

In the past five years, data science has made an impact in almost every major area of human endeavour. From commerce, to education, to energy, and of course, software and the Internet, data science has created immense value across the world. In fact, in early 2015 the President of the United States announced the new role of Chief Data Scientist to the White House and appointed DJ Patil, one of the interviewees in this book, to the position.

Like many innovations in the world, the birth of this industry was started by a few motivated people. Over the last few years, they founded, developed and advocated for the value that data analytics can bring to every industry. In The Data Science Handbook, you will have the opportunity to meet many of these founding data scientists, hear first hand accounts of the incredible journeys they took, and read where they believe the field is headed.

The road to becoming a data scientist is not always an easy one. When I tried to transition from experimental particle physics to industry, resources were few and far between. In fact, although a need for data science existed in companies, the job title had not even been created. I spent a lot of time teaching myself, working on various startup projects, and later saw many of my friends from academia run into the same challenges.

I observed a groundswell of incredibly gifted and highly trained researchers who were excited about moving into data-driven roles, yet were missing key pieces of knowledge about how to do so. As a result, they had trouble transferring their incredible quantitative and data analysis research skills to a career in industry. Meanwhile, having lived and worked in Silicon Valley, I also saw that there was very strong demand from technology companies who wanted to hire these exact people.

To help others bridge the gap between academia and industry, I founded the Insight Data Science Fellows Program in 2012. Insight is a training fellowship that helps quantitative PhDs transition from academia to industry. Over the last few years, we’ve helped hundreds of Insight Fellows, from fields like physics, computational biology, neuroscience, math, and engineering, transition from a background in academia to become leading data scientists at companies like Facebook, Airbnb, LinkedIn, The New York Times, Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center and nearly a hundred other companies.

In my personal journey to both entering the technology field as well as creating a community for others to do the same, one key resource I found to be tremendously useful was conversations with those who had successfully made the transition. As I developed Insight, I have had the chance to engage with some of Silicon Valley’s best data scientists who are mentors to the program:

Jonathan Goldman created one of the first data products at LinkedIn—People You May Know—which transformed the growth trajectory of the company. DJ Patil built and grew the data science team at LinkedIn into a powerhouse and co-coined the term “Data Scientist.” Riley Newman worked on developing product analytics that was instrumental in Airbnb’s growth. Jace Kohlmeier led the data team at Khan Academy that helped optimize learning for millions of students.

Unfortunately, it’s hard to get face-to-face time with these remarkable people. At Insight, to maintain an exceptionally high quality and personal time with these mentors, we select only a small group of talented scientists and engineers three times per year.

However, The Data Science Handbook provides readers with a way to have these in-depth conversation at scale.

By reading the interviews in The Data Science Handbook, you will have the experience of learning from the leaders in data science at your own pace, no matter where you are in the world. Each interview is an in-depth conversation, covering the personal stories of these data scientists from their initial experiences that helped them find their own path to a career in data science.

It’s not just the early data science leaders who can have a big impact on the field. There is also new talent entering, with the opportunity for each and every new member to push the field forward. When I met the authors of this book, they were still college students and aspiring data scientists, full of the same questions that those beginning in data science have.

Through 18 months of hard work, they have done the legwork in seeking out some of the best data scientists around the country, and asking them for their advice and guidance. This book is the result of that work, containing over 100 hours of collected wisdom with people otherwise inaccessible to most of us (imagine having to compete with President Obama to talk with DJ Patil!).

By reading these extended, informal interviews, you will get to sit down with industry trailblazers like DJ Patil, Jonathan Goldman and Pete Skomoroch, who were all part of the early, core LinkedIn data science teams. You will meet with Hilary Mason and Drew Conway, who were instrumental in creating the thriving New York data science community. You will hear advice from the next generation of data science leaders, like Diane Wu and Chris Moody, both Insight Alumni, who are now blazing new trails at MetaMinds and Stitch Fix.

You will meet data scientists who are having a big impact in academia, including Bradley Voytek from UC San Diego and Joe Blitzstein from Harvard. You will meet data scientists in startups, such as Clare Corthell from Mattermark and Kunal Punera of Bento Labs, who will share how they use data science as a core competitive advantage.

The data scientists in the Data Science Handbook, along with dozens of others, have helped create the very industry that is now having such a tremendous impact on the world. Here in this book, they discuss the mindset that allowed them to create this industry, address misconceptions about the field, share stories of specific challenges and victories, and talk about what they look for when building their teams.

I hope that by reading their stories, hearing how they think, and learning their vision for the future of data science, you will come to think of ways you can have an impact, and perhaps even advance the field yourself.

Jake Klamka

Founder

Insight Data Science Fellows Program
Insight Data Engineering Fellows Program
Insight Health Data Science Fellows Program

Clare Corthell

Data Scientist at Mattermark

Creating Your Own Data Science Curriculum

After graduating from Stanford, Clare Corthell embarked on a self-crafted journey to acquire the knowledge and skills to understand and analyze macro-behavioral trends. One thing led to another, and her collection of resources turned into the Open Source Data Science Masters - a curriculum of online courses, books and other resources that one could use to learn the mathematical and programming foundation crucial to a data scientist.

Clare took a risky move by crafting her own degree program, outside of traditional educational institutions. She faced skepticism of a self-taught individual in a job that is typically inhabited by PhDs, but also found a community of supportive colleagues.

Overcoming these challenges, Clare completed her Open Source Data Science Masters and found herself as a data scientist at Mattermark, a venture-backed data startup working with large datasets to help professional investors quantify and discover signals of potentially high-growth companies.

What was your background, before you began the Open Source Data Science Masters and before your role at Mattermark?

I’m a product person and an entrepreneur. I fell in love with startups long before I attended Stanford, where I designed a degree in a then-obscure program called Science, Technology & Society. You get to marry two engineering tracks, so I ended up designing a degree in product design and digital development, which then got me started working on product with early stage companies.

Before the OSDSM (Open Source Data Science Masters), I was designing and prototyping products for an early stage education technology company in Germany. Designing from user anecdotes alone became difficult when you only pull from anecdotes, so I started digging deeper into analytics and customer profiling. I started thinking about observing meta-trends among users instead of studying their behavior with a clipboard from behind a one-way window. What if I just ran several tests on two different prototypes? Then we would have data to tell us which one to develop! But as with many European startups, the company didn’t get funded, so I had a few weeks to think about how this new perspective fit in. On a long layover in Barcelona, I ordered an espresso and wrote down the technical skills I would need to dissect meta-trends and understand user data. That list laid out 6 months of full-time work, after which I’d really be able to do some damage. This became the Open Source Data Science Masters.

As with any story, it is now retrospectively clear that I would secretly fall in love with an applied statistics class I cheekily called “Exceltastic.” We worked with Bayes’ Theorem and Markov Chains in the business context, figuring out things like how many cars can pass through two toll booths per hour. Everyone else sulked and moaned through munging spreadsheets while I harbored a dirty secret: I loved Excel models! Even so, I didn’t know when my toll booth throughput calculations would be demanded of me, nor what class logically comes next. It took getting into industry to shed light on the value of keeping metrics. Things like my Exceltastic class don’t seem to fit into an overarching puzzle, but we believe they shape our path. That’s the power of confirmation bias. One of my favorite designers has this phrase that he prints in various media: “Everything I do always comes back to me.” I’ve always found that fitting.

What is the Open Source Data Science Masters? What does its curriculum look like?

It’s a collection of open-source resources that help a programmer acquire the skills necessary to be a competent entry-level data scientist. The first version included introductory linear algebra, statistics, databases, algorithms, graph analysis, data mining, natural language processing, and machine learning. I wrote the curriculum for myself, then I realized that people all over the internet were asking for it, so I published it on GitHub.

In August, I opened the curriculum for pull requests on GitHub. Without feedback it’s difficult to know whether you’ve covered the right things. Further, it was an effort to get feedback on the idea of an institution-free degree, a kind of home-school for advanced degrees. The internet was astonishingly supportive and excited - and that excitement is addictive. It makes you want to be more transparent, and to become part of other peoples’ wonder in learning new things.

How did you get started with the Open Source Data Science Masters?

I knew that a traditional Masters program would take at least the next three years of my life, but even more importantly it wouldn’t focus on what is core to the profession I wanted to enter. I knew what I wanted and I was willing to take the risk of a non-institution education.

I set out for the curriculum to take 6 months to complete (March - August 2013), with a small project at the end and various programming mini-projects focusing on scraping, modeling, and analysis. It was amazing how difficult it was to manage myself. School gives you this structure that you don’t have to question or design, which you don’t really see until you have to manage your own curriculum and deadlines. There’s a lot of product management that goes into an educational track like the OSDSM. I’m grateful to all the people who supported me and helped me throughout, even if they didn’t quite understand the strange and uncharted waters I was braving to get there.

How did you find the resources?

I reverse-engineered most of it from job descriptions that interested me. This meant companies I believed would grow quickly and provide the most opportunity: mid-stage startups, 100-200 people, existing data science teams and reverence for the methodology. I didn’t want to be the lone wolf and knew I needed mentorship.

People tend to frown on centering the goals of the classroom on applicability in the real world, but a classic liberal educational approach in a technical career pivot won’t serve you. This is a technical vocational degree, so the goal was very concrete. I should be employable and employed on a data science (or Analytics Engineering) team after completing the curriculum.

There was another realization that coalesced very quickly: the act of designing from insights of single users does not scale. I was also hankering for something more technically and algorithmically challenging. I’d bought this book before I moved to Germany, Programming Collective Intelligence. I just bought it, I really had no reason to. When I first opened it up, I understood next to nothing. But I carried it with me in Germany, and every time I opened it, something new jumped out and I understood more about scaling user insight. The book became my cornerstone, how I measured my progress. It’s a bible for Data Scientists.

I also used the following resources/websites:

Quora

This is a great resource for the Valley - it’s truly navel-gazing, but if that’s what you’re doing, it’s useful. People like DJ have answered questions about what a Data Scientist does on a daily basis. You can start to discern the technical capacities that are required of you, mathematical foundations that are necessary, and so forth.

Blogs

Zipfian Academy, a data science bootcamp, had a blog. They had a great post on the resources they saw as core to becoming a data scientist: A Practical Intro to Data Science

Coursera

I’m Coursera’s biggest fanboy. They’re part of this quietly-brewing educational revolution, which will soon be less quiet. My story is a tremor before the earthquake, I’m just waiting for the ground to start shaking.

How much math (probability, statistics, ML) did you try to learn? How much math do you think a data scientist needs to know?

You don’t have to know everything. That’s why I’ve tried to keep the curriculum so tightly focused on its goal. Programmers are great at “just-in-time” learning because it’s impossible to know everything. That’s a great trait. If you have a core set of competencies and understand how to “debug” problems and learn what you need to solve them, you can do damage. And naturally, you improve over time by recognizing new problems as chunks of old problems you’ve already seen and solved.

So much of this curriculum is abstract, and that’s where people get scared. People are scared of math because it’s not applied in our education system. But those scary elements of math and abstraction diminish with concrete examples and conversations with others. I had a few phone-a-friend lifelines, and I ate up Khan Academy and Coursera videos. There’s something magical about how much more communicative spoken English can be, especially when you can rewind and digest a concept for the second, third, or even fourth time. You can always talk through a problem with someone else, even if they’re not an expert. Talking through things is synonymous with debugging. One of my mentors calls this “the rubber ducky method,” because if you talk a problem through to a plastic duck, sometimes you start to find the holes in your assumptions. Then you can plug them up.

If you think about people as having different levels of competency in these different realms, it doesn’t take long to understand that working as a team allows you to stack your respective skills on top of one another. Having specialties among the team is really essential to getting things done in a small organization. I was lucky enough to join a company where I get mentorship in verticals where I’m middling or even an amateur. It’s amazing to learn with other people. Finding a job where you have mentors and training is essential to continue to grow and improve. And if you’re not improving and growing, you’re dead in the water. So that’s a long-winded way of saying: Working with other people is essential to working with more complex concepts and systems. Rome wasn’t built by some guy, and probably not at a weekend hackathon.

What would you do differently if you could redo the Masters?

As Patient Zero of a new type of internet-based institution-free education, I didn’t know what to expect. It was impossible to know how I would be judged and whether I would benefit from my experiment. This type of ambiguity usually makes people extremely uncomfortable. It’s like leaving a six-year-old in the library by herself instead of putting her in class with a teacher. What is she going to do? Pull a bunch of books onto the floor and see how high she can stack them? Watch birds at the window and think about how wings work? Or is she going to find something interesting and gather books that will help her form her own ideas about the world?

I knew that it would be a risk, but I took a leap of faith and left myself alone in the library. In the end, the greatest reward didn’t come from the curriculum, it came from what taking a risk demonstrated about me. It led me to a tribe that respected the risk I had taken, and valued the grit that it required to follow through. Many people were displeased that I let myself into the library without an adult. But I’m not interested in taking the recommended path and clinging to a librarian. I have no interest in small ambition.

What’s the difference between data science job descriptions & day-to-day role at Mattermark?

Our CEO Danielle was once asked how many data scientists we have at Mattermark. We’re all data scientists, she thought - we all use, manipulate, and analyze data on a daily basis to make our customers happier and more profitable. We even all write SQL! That’s not something you see every day at a company, but it’s essential when you’re building and selling a data product. I build products as an engineer, anything from fitting clustering algorithms, building automated analyses, designing UIs, acquiring new data - it’s a startup. It’s all hands on deck.

It’s not clear that data science is a job title to stay yet. For example, do we know if growth hacking is a subset of data science? We don’t. There will always be a top-level salary for a person who can turn chaos into insights. That won’t change. Data Scientist is a title we’ll continue to use while we figure it out.

What could someone in school, or otherwise without too much background in industry learn from your experience?

The ability to evolve my own career with a self-designed curriculum begins to outline the immense cracks in the foundation of higher education*. The deconstruction of this system was very long in coming, but it’s happening now. The lesson is the following: if you take initiative and acquire skills that increment your value, the market is able and willing to reward you.

Though people continue to believe and espouse old patterns of education and success, these patterns do not represent requirements or insurance. The lack of any stamp of approval is a false barrier. There are no rules.

It’s important to understand the behavior of the market and institutions with regard to your career. When breaking out of the patterns of success, know that people will judge you differently than others who have followed the rules.

There are two very discrete things that I learned: The market is requiring people to perform tryouts for jobs instead of interviews, and most companies don’t hire for your potential future value.

Tryouts as Interviews: The economy has set a very high bar for people coming into a new profession. Job descriptions always describe a requirement for previous experience, which is paradoxical because you need experience to get it. Don’t let that scare you, not for a minute. Pull on your bootstraps and get in the door by giving yourself that experience - design and execute on a project that demonstrates your ability to self-lead. Demonstrate that you can take an undefined problem and design a solution. It will give you the confidence, the skills, and the background to merit everything from the first interview to the salary you negotiate.

Even more concretely, work with a non-profit organization (or another organization that doesn’t have the economic power to hire programmers or data scientists) to create a project that is meaningful for the organization and also shows off your skills. It’s a great way to do demonstrative and meaningful work while also aiding an organization that could use your help, and likely has problems people are paying attention to solving. Win-win.

Current Value vs Potential: Look for companies that will hire you for your potential. It’s important to be upfront about your grit, self-sufficiency, and ability to hit the ground running. Luckily, with disciplines like data science, the market is on your side. Sometimes companies can spring for a Junior Data Scientist and invest in your growth, which is really what you wanted from the beginning.

Everyone will tell you this, but I work on product so I’ll underline it even more strongly: Learn to write production-level code. The more technical you are, the more valuable you are. Being able to write production code makes you imminently hirable and trainable.

[NB: Don’t think for a minute that I don’t believe in the tenets of a true liberal education - quite the contrary. I continue to read philosophy and history, in part because we cannot draw fully upon the knowledge of man without doing so. These are essential elements to being a purposed, ethical, and effective person - but they don’t directly accelerate a career. The true liberal education has nothing to do with market forces, and never should. Higher Education as it exists today and Liberal Education should be held as wholly uniquely-motivated institutions.]*

How was your self-taught path to becoming a data scientist received by company recruiters? What advice would you share with entrepreneurial individuals who are interested in the field?

Talk with people who can recognize hustle and grit, and not necessarily those who are looking to match a pattern drawn from your previous experience. Often, these kinds of people run startups.

Recruiters gave me a very real response: They didn’t see my course of self-study as legitimate. It’s hard to give yourself a stamp of approval and be taken seriously. I wouldn’t recommend that just anyone do what I did - it will take a while for autodidactism to become more accepted, and maybe it will never be a primary pattern. But maybe people like me can help expose this as a viable way to advance professionally. I know that great companies like Coursera will continue to innovate on these new forms of education, keep quality high, and democratize access.

tl;dr

If you want to get to the next level, wherever your next level may be, it’s possible to pave your own road that leads you there. It’s a monstrously tough road, but it’s your road.

Chris Moody

Data Scientist at Stitch Fix

Astrophysics to Data Science

Chris Moody started off his journey towards data science by peering off into distant galaxies, studying computational astrophysics at UC Santa Cruz as a graduate student.

As the data revolution hit the fields of science, however, Chris found himself having to learn how to use more sophisticated tools that could process more data. He dove into programming and contributing towards open-source astrophysics projects.

All this culminated in a data science fellowship at Insight Data Science. After completing his Fellowship, Chris joined Square’s Data Science team. After leaving Square, Chris is now a data scientist at Stitch Fix, a fashion startup.

Thank you very much for being with us, Chris. Can you tell us a little bit about your background?

I went to Caltech as an undergrad to study Physics. There, I had projects that were largely computational.

For example, a project I was involved in was looking at dark matter simulations. Basically, we don’t know that much about dark matter, but we can guess at things that it could possibly do. One of those things is that it could decay. If it decays, the dark matter particle gets a kick, and it goes off in a random direction at a random speed. Galaxies are sitting at the bottom of a gravity well; they’re like bread crumbs in a big bowl of dark matter. If the dark matter were spontaneously decaying and getting lots of extra energy, it could popcorn out, and totally change the profiles of galaxies in an essential way. This was a strongly computational project that taught me many skills.

After Caltech, I came to Santa Cruz for graduate studies, still working in computational astrophysics. While I was there, I was doing all sorts of things pertaining to galaxies. We would look through the Hubble Space Telescope at the youngest galaxies in the universe and notice that they were not at all like the galaxies today. Galaxies today are beautiful spiral structures. But when you look back at the youngest galaxies, they are lumpy and clumpy… they look like soup.

So, one of the questions was: Does that mesh well with our ideas of how our universe formed? We started to look at the simulations and realized that what we observed through the telescope is what we were seeing in our simulations. We were super surprised at these theoretical predictions coming true!

The next part followed the standard trajectory of a lot of businesses. We got one or two really positive examples of galaxies matching our predictions, and were very excited about the progress. But it was only one or two examples; we wanted to know if this was statistically significant, and so we started to scale up our data. We exploded from 100 gigabytes to hundreds of terabytes of data. This all started at the NASA Ames supercomputer.

It turns out that it’s really hard to answer simple questions when those questions don’t fit onto one computer. So we had to scale up a lot of our algorithms, and build our own infrastructure and framework. It was at that point that we started to get really interesting results. We started to see that this is generally true, and this attracted a lot of people to our project, scaling up our people power. So we’d get other new graduate student astronomers and explain, ‘This is how we work; this is how you can be efficient.’

I think the romantic, public idea of a scientist is that you jump into a cave and then five months later, you have a “Eureka” moment and you come out. Then it’s glorious. But that’s not really how it works. The reality is: you have lots of bugs, you make lots of errors, and you have to work as a team, which means you have to be able to work efficiently. You have to know how a pull request works. You have to know how commits work. You have to know how to document. You have to file bugs and report to issue trackers. You have to do all of these things.

At the end of all that, I realized that I most liked working with data. I liked working with algorithms. Actually, I absolutely loved working with algorithms.

I spent more time reading about how the algorithms worked and how they found all this truth, despite all the noise and red herrings in the data. I loved doing that and working with people on a project together. It was great. I thought galaxies were cool, don’t get me wrong, but I liked algorithms more.

It sounds like you spotted a project, saw that it was interesting and used your experience of working on it to explore your interests. How did your background in science inform your work as a data scientist?

Science is getting harder to do. It’s harder to do it individually and it has to happen as part of a team; a collaborative effort, so we can measure different things. Looking at papers from 50 years ago: having a paper with 50 authors on it was ridiculous, that just never happened. Half the papers out there were published with only one or two authors on them.

Now, that’s ridiculously absurd. I can’t remember the last time I read a paper with only one author on it.

It’s just because the instruments you have to use are larger. We end up having to use supercomputer resources or we have to use the Hubble Space Telescope to get somewhere. This means that the data and ideas are starting to grow much larger than one person can manage. In turn, it means that you have to learn how to work with other people. So that’s a paradigm shift of science, and also something that I think industry has been familiar with for a much longer period of time.

At the same time, a lot of my exposure to things like software engineering best practices, or even computer science, was completely self-taught. I didn’t take any formal classes in these fields.

That’s really interesting that it worked out so well, and also that that didn’t hinder you.

I think that’s actually pretty normal. Look at some start-ups. They’re really interested in finding someone who can actually do the work; someone who is trying to find and build a whole community and foster that growth. Take that person from the 90th percentile and just teach them the remaining 10% of the small skills needed. These startups are basically instilling habits; thinking about what you’re going to do and how it’s going to reflect on everyone else in the network, instead of being an isolated person.

Sometimes, that has to happen as a feedback reflex. You have to think of how you’re going to fit in with everything else. You have to think about how your code is going to be used by others. I was lucky in that I had a community leader in my project who was really interested in teaching everyone else how to work together, and I learned a lot from him.

Of your friends and peers from Caltech, many of whom have also gone on to do heavy computational physics research, have you found that a substantial portion of them are heading towards industry?

Yes, especially in astrophysics. I can’t tell you how many plots I have seen in the last year with the number of faculty jobs remaining constant, or maybe even slightly decreasing with time, compared with the sky-high number of post doctorates. That means that the likelihood of a post doctorate job opening is going down at a ridiculous rate. Even when I was in graduate school, the expected number of postdoctoral candidates went from two to three. If it kept going at that rate, by the time I’d finished my first post doctorate, the expected rate would be four postdocs to every one position.

Clearly, there’s a huge supply of post doctorates and not that many positions within academia.

How much did those academic job statistics influence your decision on what you wanted to do after graduate school? Did you feel you could get the same intellectual stimulation from problems in industry as you received in academia?

Yes, it was a hard decision, but you look at it and think, ‘How many times do I really want to roll the dice? How much do I really like this?’ That fear of not finding a job really destroys a lot of the romance of science. I feel like a lot of people start doing science because they have this romantic notion of becoming the best scientist, or contributing in a noble way. But the truth is that science is a shitty ride.

You can do a lot of the same things that science will let you do, but you don’t have to do these things in the world of academia. You can work on science in industry. When I made that realization, and understood I could do a lot of the science, and be involved in a lot of the cool stuff I’d tried to do in the first place, it made me realize that I could switch to a new job outside of academia. At the same time, I didn’t feel that I was giving up on what drove me initially. There are a lot of startups that are changing the world, so instead of trying to define clumps and galaxies, I could try to actually work with somebody, and try to change the world. I thought this was really cool and super exciting.

So then you joined Insight – a six week long Fellowship for PhDs looking to enter the field of data science. How much of what the Fellowship taught you would you say was new to you?

All of it. There’s a paradigm shift from science and industry. Everything in science is about a fully detailed presentation of an idea; exhaustively explicating all of the caveats. All of the communication is bordered on fully defined facts, or at least as much as possible. You look at the borders of your project, the borders of the results, and you know the downsides and you know the upsides, and that’s because you’re terrified that someone will find a deficit in your project, and then nail you for it.

But then the opposite is true in business. The biggest problem is that people have very limited bandwidth. It takes a lot of effort, and there are a lot of people demanding it. So the crux of everything in business is actually being able to move all of your results in as terse and precise a fashion as possible.

You don’t need to delineate all of the possibilities, you just need to say what is the major point, and you can go on from there. So, a lot of what Insight taught me was that you need to condense all of your results down as quickly as possible. You get someone’s attention and you go; that’s the hardest part. As scientists, we were taught to give an hour-long lecture on our project. We didn’t have to consider whether our audience was being entertained or not. If they’re not interested, you don’t care. They’re not your audience if they weren’t interested in the first place.

It’s the opposite idea during the Insight Data Science Fellowship. You have to go out and you have to make every single connection for yourself. You have to boil it down and make it completely convincing that everything you’re saying is relevant to them, and you have to do it in 5 seconds. Everything is an elevator pitch. Every YC Company has to give demos in 180 seconds. So Insight is all about building a demo in those 6 weeks, and then pitching it in 180 seconds. You’re basically pitching yourself as a candidate to those companies. You’re saying, ‘Don’t look at me like a graduate student. I’m actually super goal-orientated, or systems-orientated. I can take all this data, apply these algorithms, and give you some amazing results.’ That’s what those three minutes are for, and that’s the whole paradigm shift. Now, the focus is not so much on the new idea or how much you’ve added to the body of knowledge. The focus is what can you tell me in 100 seconds. That’s all the CEO has time for.

In scientific lectures, you’re not trying to reach a super-broad audience. In the case of science, you’re trying to deliver an idea, and then you try to back it up in 15,000 words.

You need to do that in business as well. You need to be able to take your idea and defend it. The thing is that, here, you’re no longer trying to defend it to the CEO, you’re no longer trying to defend it to anyone else. You just need to defend it to yourself, and then you need to give them the ideas; there’s an implicit trust there.

No one else is going to check your work and no one else should check your work. You need to be an independent party and you need to break it down as to what is important.

You have to build up small kernels of truth, and that’s all you can deliver. A lot of the time, people find it distressing, but I thought it was great. I thought it was an awesome challenge to be able to compress my message down and figure out what all the tidbits are. It’s like a whole design philosophy. I liked the idea of throwing out everything except for what you need to function. I like it from a designer standpoint and also from an algorithms and data analysis standpoint. I think that embodying that philosophy was the single most successful part of the Insight Fellowship.

“Data science” has now become a very common phrase in many business sectors. Yet, it’s still nebulous and no one is really sure what it means. So, what does data science mean to you? How would you break it down?

It means a lot. It always means to measure data, being able to make sense of that data, create models of that data, and most importantly, to be able to communicate what that data means.

I think data science splits into two fields, and I believe a lot of hiring companies are starting to reflect this. Data science is starting to break off into descriptive analytics and predictive analytics.

Descriptive analytics is, ‘we saw this trend.’ Or, for example, ‘We saw this spike or dip… is that because our service crashed? We saw this huge spike…is it a multiplicity of things?’ It’s always asking questions of dynamics, and then asking what is going on. So the raw data comes back, and then you make something useful – actionable business intelligence – from that data. That’s descriptive analytics, taking data that has been produced and trying to make head or tails out of it, to drive some decisions out of it. So that might mean, ‘We saw some really exciting events in Bulgaria, but why is our site exploding in Bulgaria and nowhere else?’ You may find out that it’s not really from Bulgaria, or that it’s raining everywhere else, or a volcano just went off and everybody’s Tweeting about it, or something ridiculous like that.

The other side of data science is predictive analytics; being ahead of the game. This is where you’re shifting towards machine learning algorithms. You’re looking at things such as fraud, where you’re trying to predict whether a transaction is fraudulent or not. Or, you’re trying to figure out security applications: is this malevolent activity? But that’s what it is, fundamentally. It’s pattern finding within all the data, in real-time, which adds additional constraints on computational complexity.

Data science rapidly becoming something concrete, especially as it becomes a more well-defined field. But it’s definitely splitting off into those two directions of data, analyzing it and figuring out underlying trends. If there are multiple trends, maybe it’s multiple elements stacking up to produce the signal you’re looking at. Maybe it’s not really a signal at all, and it’s a bug somewhere, so you have to look at the data.

The other side is not just trying to make heads or tails of the data, but also making predictions. Which city are we going to open up in next? What are the relevant quantities? A lot of business is driven by intuition and gut feelings, and this scares a lot of people. CEOs are trying to pitch entire companies on feelings, essentially. They’re trying to drive home their points on a colloquial basis. The whole field of data science is trying to turn that feeling into something a little more rigorous; trying to deliver on something that’s not intuition, and finding something that you can ground yourself on. That gives your business a lot of stability, especially when there’s a lot of startups and they’re all thinking of great ideas, but only some of them are really as great as they believe, and most of them won’t pan out.

You engage a data scientist at the point when you’re looking to add an incremental value. That’s not going to make your business take off, it’s not guaranteed. But at least it will give you something that’s not solely based on a feeling.

Of the two different types of data science you articulated, do they also require different skills?

For the most part, they require a lot of the same core skills. Predictive data science requires a little more machine learning type skills, and descriptive probably requires a lot more statistical skills. But then, in predictive data analysis, you might be using a lot more random forests or neural networks – all these really cool algorithms.

Which side of data science, from your physics background, seems more intuitive with you?

I started learning programming In high school, because I wanted to play around with genetic algorithms. So that’s been a long running interest. Even though I went off and did experimental physics and computational astrophysics, I’ve always had this background of really wanting to do machine learning. That appeals more to the predictive side than the descriptive side. Both of them have a lot of overlap. There’s not a wall between the two, but you can start to see the continuum of data science. So, I think I’m far more attracted to the predictive side. Neural networks I just think are really cool because you’re essentially training artificial intelligence. You’re taking these tiny artificial brains and making a decision with them. You’re actually turning a whole company based on that.

What do you feel are the defining qualities of a top-notch data scientist, compared with someone who is merely good?

I think it deals with communication. I think that’s the difference between the good scientists and the great. Both are going to know a lot about statistics, the techniques they can use, and how to design, implement, and execute an experiment. Those things are all important. The biggest thing, though, is that you need to be able to communicate those results. That’s a lot harder than it looks.

I think the easiest thing for a graduate student to do, coming into this field, is to gloss over it, but that’s the single most important thing. Most people complain that graduate students don’t have a great programming background. All of their other intuitions, well designed experiments, caveated results, are sound. But I think that a lot of people believe that a programming background is not necessary.

So, maybe it is programming for a lot of people, but if you’re already pretty good, then you’re probably already a good programmer. The last step is just communication. People need to sense the passion inside of you. This defines the most successful people. It’s the realization that you are working with other people, and for a lot of scientists, I think that’s quite a shock. It really goes against this notion of romantic science.

Isaac Newton spent three years in a shack during the plague. He didn’t want to get the plague and he hated talking to everyone. Granted, he was possibly autistic in some ways, but I think a lot of people follow that archetype of going back and living by themselves, and then they emerge with all of their findings. But in reality, it needs to be a much more continuous process. It needs to be a much smoother process than just coming back and reeling off a list of accomplishments. So it’s always communication, but that’s the easiest part to skip over.

What do you see as the promise with data science, and also the interplay between mathematics and computer science, that really speaks to you? Where does your passion lie?

We’re living in a really exciting time because I think what were formerly highly theoretical principles are finally having an impact on the world. Before, I was looking at clumps and galaxies. To do that I needed to run clustering algorithms. I needed to be able to run distributed frameworks on thousands of nodes to answer basic questions.

Now, I can do almost the same stuff, and I can tweak a learning algorithm that teaches students in the best way they can learn. There’s a whole feedback system that says, “you should answer these questions, and then five minutes from now, we’ll come back and repeat it, and then we’ll come back a week later and repeat it again.”

The wonderful thing is that those algorithms, that whole pattern, is being replicated from galaxies to psychology and cognition. All of these high topics of knowledge are beginning to trickle down, and they’re actually making a real impact on day-to-day interactions. There is not a single company on NASDAQ that doesn’t use some aspect of this. Your Facebook Newsfeed is highly tweaked to give you everything that you think is relevant, and new content to test your preferences.

LinkedIn is using all kinds of graph networks. Square is using all these fraud detection techniques. HealthTap is fielding all of these questions, and training a computer to understand what these questions are. And there really are doctors who will be answering a lot of those medical questions.

The cool thing here is that they can take a doctor and clone him virtually. He can answer a question, and that might reduce patient time in a hospital somewhere. And when you take that power, and you multiply it by the number of patients in the whole world – it’s a huge number. These are real things. We’re not limited to theoretical worlds. You really can go out and have awesome effects immediately, and they’re tangible. We’re collecting more and more data, to the point that there are not that many aspects of life that aren’t becoming data driven. So it’s super exciting.

Imagine if you were able to go back to the beginning of your graduate school career, and you meet yourself coming in the corridors and you have a five minute window to speak to yourself. Would you tell yourself to do anything differently?

A lot of it would have centered on working more with people. I joined an open source project, and that was the single best decision in all of graduate school. I learned how to code in a collaborative way.

The second most important thing probably would have been communication. Every week, I would deliver a presentation on my results during the past week, and usually, it would boil down to giving a two or three minute feedback session at the end of that. So I was already doing a lot of communication and I wouldn’t have changed that.

My programming context was great; maybe I should have started that earlier and taken more formal programming classes. If you were to design the curriculum, I’d say you have to have a lot of programming. A lot of classes are like, ‘go and do this assignment.’ The real world is, ‘go do this assignment but you only have to do this module, and someone else will do the next module. You guys need to be working collaboratively.’

They should also be doing lots of statistics, and they should be able to do it as quickly as possible. People love to talk about this Pareto Principle, where 80% of the outcomes result from 20% of the effort. The hard part is trying to figure out where that 80% line actually is, and once you realize you’re at it, stop.

How can people find open source projects to participate in?

A lot of the time, they already exist. You probably already know what they are because you hear about them. The biggest thing is not to be shy about it, and not to be scared off. It took me a long time to work up the courage to actually push code back out and be able to take the criticism. No matter where you’re working, there are other people working with similar problems. Just go out and search for them. If they haven’t solved your specific niche problem, join the effort. It’s a worthwhile process. It’s really hard to convince graduate students about this, who are already overwhelmed with a lot of other things, but it is definitely the best part of those five years.

Your advisor is going to be pushing you for results, and my advisor said it had been years since he’d written any code. So you might not realize how important this is. But in a world that is becoming way more team-based, both in industry and science, it’s super important to push everything into a team-based context.

Also, if you’re in science, you’re all about trying to communicate your results. One of the best ways to do that is through your open source network. They have an audience there, waiting for you, and they might be really interested. A lot of it is, ‘I built this feature onto this project.’ They’ll go try it out and maybe they’ll write a paper about it, and then you get an extra citation.

There are a lot of extra indirect effects. The direct effect is that you’ll be better. The indirect effects are that there are a lot of other people who will benefit, and that will reflect very well on you.

It’s a little unfortunate that the primary currency of science is citations and not source code, even though that’s a big infrastructure push. I think that will have to change going forward because everything is being done in a team-based context. To do science more efficiently, it has to be that way. There’s no other alternative.

Erich Owens

Data Engineer at Facebook

The Importance of Software Engineering in Data Science

Erich sits at the intersection of data science and engineering, a role derived from his unique experiences across academia, quantitative analysis and software engineering. After training as an applied mathematician at Brown, Erich cut his teeth at Quid analysing an eclectic set of data. From Quid, he moved on to Facebook where he currently works as as data-centric software engineer - combining his deep theoretical understanding of mathematics with good software engineering skills.

He stresses the importance of coalescing different silos of knowledge and working with a business owner mindset to prioritise important pieces of work.

Please talk a little about your background and how you ended up at Facebook?

I studied mathematics and applied mathematics during college. I started with a focus on mathematics and physics at a small liberal arts college called Albion. I then transferred to Columbia University where I obtained a bachelor of science in applied mathematics.

I worked at the Stanford Linear Accelerator and the Nasa Jet Propulsion Lab doing basic research in materials science and systems engineering. I then transitioned to a Ph.D. program in applied mathematics at Brown University, but dropped out after two years with a masters degree as I couldn’t see myself spending seven years on partial differential equations.

I moved out to California to work for startups. I realized that the most exciting thing for me was data science and machine learning. I spent two years at startups called Quid and Newsle and then joined Facebook four months ago as a software engineer with a bent towards machine learning and data science.

It sounds like you have this background in mathematics and you mentioned that you wanted to do more machine learning. Could you talk a little bit about how you picked data science versus the other things you could’ve done in industry?

I guess when you’re a student at Columbia or Brown and you’re looking at what kind of jobs there are, finance is a recurring theme. You go and interview for quant jobs and you realize how there is this massive glut of smart people learning how to game arbitrage with marginal returns. In the grand scheme of things, finance just seemed fruitless.

Compare that to the Bay area, where you have people learning how to build recommender systems, teaching systems to learn and that to me is very exciting. I think personally that move seemed accessible to someone with a mathematics background. It required heavy use of high dimensional vector spaces, linear programs, kernel methods, etc., which was a language I spoke already.

On the contrary, server client protocols and the more computer science concepts were foreign to me.

You mentioned this a little bit earlier concerning your move into machine learning and data science. Now that you’re at Facebook, what would you say is the value that you add as a data scientist?

In the case of Quid, they had a whole team of data analysts who were interested in having humans label training data. For them to scale, it wasn’t about hiring hundreds of more people, but it was about teaching an algorithm to do what the analysts did. Their move is largely emblematic of the growth potential of Silicon Valley, where you get exponential returns by scaling hardware instead of people.

I think finding people who could play around in Python and C++ and build these learning systems was hard.

Briefly going back to your previous experience in academia, what would you say were your biggest challenges in doing research positions at SLAC or your Ph.D. program to your roles at Quid, Newsle or Facebook?

Academics don’t really learn to code the way engineers in the Bay Area do. You learn as an academic to hack together code to produce results for your research. There is no incentive to learn to code well or maintainably. You don’t think about object orientation, functional programming or other techniques in the academic environment, which can be an impediment.

Wearing a business hat also provides a higher-level end goal which is sometimes not present in the academic environment.

How did you overcome these challenges?

I first joined Quid as a quantitative analyst and I had a very basic level of Python skills from academia. Fortunately some engineers at Quid took me under their wings and taught the basics of good software engineering.

I think when you are a student in mathematics or physics, you think vector is a vector or a matrix is a matrix, but you don’t really think about how those representations tie into the computer. You don’t think about sparsity, run-time, etc., which are very important in industry.

Throughout our conversations we’ve talked to many people about their data science background because there is such a diverse set of ways for people to get into the field. What would you have done differently through school and work given the experiences you’ve acquired?

I wish I plunged in more to build things, building websites or projects. When you’re comfortable writing things on a whiteboard, you get scared of code. I think iterating a lot on a prototype is really empowering and lets you learn programming and languages.

I wish I had programmed more, because when I first moved to Silicon Valley, lack of coding skills was a big stumbling block. I think my roles at the earlier startups also demanded a lot of iteration and prototyping, which helped me learn a lot. The pressure to see results in industry made the learning process a lot quicker compared to if I were learning in school.

What would you say is the value that you bring to Facebook as a data scientist?

The value I bring is not so much as a data scientist, but as a software engineer. Although I borrow the tools of data science in terms of clustering , data analysis and classifiers, I have the ability to build a scalable full-stack system. So I am not just building stand-alone models which are pretty to look at which I’ll write a paper about, but where I add real value is by incorporating that model into a scalable system.

It’s really interesting that you say that because we’ve talked to people who say that their main value is not software engineering, but rather their quantitative skills. Of the people you’ve worked with, how many tend to come from the math to engineering transition and vice-versa?

Facebook has its own data science team which is full of brilliant academics. I talk to them to get advice on what features to build and what algorithms.

Having that isolated academic data science team is really useful for an engineer like me. We wouldn’t be as successful without them.

I sit at the intersection of data science and engineering.

Can you talk a little bit about where data science in Facebook sits in the organizational chart or the product pipeline?

I’m on the public content ranking team. We want to connect you to content that you may like. So in a sense we’re working on a content delivery system.

In order for that to work, you really have to understand how newsfeed-ranking algorithms work and what the goal for that team is. It’s one thing to rank and display your friends’ content which is quite a finite problem, it’s another to aggregate all content on Facebook at a given time to enable content discovery. The problem is much broader than that.

Data science at Facebook is a stand-alone organization, but I’ve met several data scientists who have been embedded in different groups. So the structure depends on the product. On some teams, data is used to inform product decisions, on others data is a core component.

In some ways these silos of data science remind one of Bell Labs, where you build great things and are not so worried from week to week about the details of short-term projects or metric gains.

So you’re more insulated from the hard product deadlines and have more freedom to explore?

That would be my guess, but I am a software engineer. I think that would be accurate as the data science team does publish a lot of papers with the data Facebook collects.

You’ve been in a lot of roles from startups to Facebook, and you’ve surely met a lot of data scientists along the way. What would you say are some of the qualities that separate the best data scientists from the rest?

The brilliant ones I’ve seen at the few companies I’ve worked at were the ones who could read papers, prototype and then turn it into a scalable system. I’ve met quite a few people who would have a great idea, but would then take forever to implement it even in Matlab.

So I think strong programming skills coupled with systems-level thinking is very important. Building scalable systems may limit your ideas, but it makes them that much more powerful in terms of impact. At Quid, for instance, there were engineers who could build systems on their own and think theoretically. In my opinion, the combination of strong theory and the ability to implement that in a scalable manner are makes a data scientist stand out.

Are there any developments in the field of data science and machine learning that really excite you?

I like the idea of wearable computing, for instance Google Glass. Say you’re in this neighborhood and you want coffee, but Glass could recommend a nearby art gallery. I like the idea of life recommendations, the idea of personal assistance, the idea of picking up on personal signals and making recommendations.

More advanced algorithms based off linear separations like support vector machines (SVMs) or deep neural networks that could learn intermediary steps or do automated feature engineering are very exciting.

Say at some point that you would like to move on; do you think that your background would facilitate an easy transition to another field?

I’ve thought about hypotheticals, where say in 10 years I’ve built a great career at Facebook and might go back to school to study quantum computers or some exciting technology at the time.

Having a strong mathematical background really emboldens you to do these things. The nature of hiring at that age is different as you would no longer be a fresh college graduate, but an experienced hire. At that point, you may also have enough experience to start your own company in an adjacent field.

How do you approach problems? What’s a mathematical way of approaching data science problems and how do you use that framework to solve other problems?

I’ll give you an example. When looking at time series of data, one usually opts for analyzing the entire data set which requires a large amount of memory to store, which will impede actual analysis.

Having learned mathematics and signal theory, I could use a low-pass filter and just keep a small buffer to learn the exponential moving average at any given time. You see how an analog-to-digital converter can be useful in analyzing social data. I think spotting analogous metaphors between fields is the most useful thing someone from a rigorous background can do.

Just building off analogous metaphors – simulated annealing was inspired by metallurgy. How have you found your background in mathematics useful in cross-pollinating ideas to your current role at Facebook?

When it comes to recommendation systems, people will often use singular value decomposition (SVD) to do dimensionality reduction. For me that makes sense from a mathematical background, but I’ve seen stumbling blocks when talking to engineers about why that concept would be useful.

The ability to read a paper and understand it is also very useful. For instance there is this beautiful technique called random projections where you populate a random projection matrix using ones, zeros and minus ones, scaled by some normalization term. You can throw such a projection matrix against a high-dimensional vector and map it to a lower-dimensional space. According to the Johnson Lindenstrauss lemma, you can guarantee with high probability that the interpoint distances will be mostly consistent. It’s a remarkable property because you basically scatter your data into the wind, but it’s still useful with the added benefits of easier implementations and lower runtimes. It makes sense in terms of probability, but it seems really non-intuitive otherwise.

What advice or feedback would you give to people who are just starting out on their transition to the industry?

I think the most useful thing about being in college and graduate school for so many years was that I was learning for the sake of it and it was just very interesting. When I was doing applied mathematics I ironically wasn’t that interested in applications. When I asked myself what I wanted during graduate school, I would say that I wanted the autonomy to work on some really big and hard problems. That was as concrete as my career goals were.

I’m really lucky that the whole data science and machine learning industry existed when I got out of school. I worry that if I were pragmatically focused on learning certain things, I might miss more abstract concepts which have greater implications later.

So I guess I would encourage people to study what they like, but the way that worked out for me may not work for others. It’s difficult to give very specific advice.

Eithon Cadag

Data Scientist at Ayasdi

Bridging the Chasm: From Biomedical Informatics to Data Science

After dual degrees at the University of Washington followed by a PhD in Biomedical Informatics, Eithon came to data science through a focus on machine learning applied to biology. Although initially disinterested in low level programming, Eithon came to see the powerful application areas during his research and wrote a pipeline that is still used to identify pathogenic proteins for structure crystallization.

*After graduating, he worked on defense projects for various US government agencies, before striking into the heart of Silicon Valley. At the time of this interview, Eithon was a manager and principal data scientist at topological machine learning company Ayasdi, where he led analytical efforts in the healthcare and pharmaceutical space. In this interview, Eithon talks about his personal journey to data science mastery, and the joy of being insatiably curious. *

Can you talk a little bit about your background?

I double degreed at the University of Washington in Business and Informatics; the latter is a specialized degree that focuses on data architecture and how people interact with data and information.

I originally thought of Computer Science as a major, but took a few classes and realized I didn’t want to be coding all at the time. So I opted for an option that potentially didn’t involve significant programming, but did involve many things that you would typically see when working on applied technical problems.

My undergrad focus was on Ubiquitous Computing, and my undergrad capstone project was on embedded barcoding and handheld computing. I can attribute this to my first job during college, which was at Intel Research in Seattle. At the time, the Lab’s stated focus was on ubiquitous computing; this means embedding computing into your environment or finding ways of using computing in ways well-integrated to the environment.

I worked on two research projects there: LabScape and PlaceLab. LabScape asked the question, “How can we embed computing systems within research laboratories to help scientists?” Basically, we’d develop studies on how scientists actually use software in the lab. PlaceLab, the second project, asked “Can we utilize WiFi devices to triangulate position and provide location-specific information to a user?” Have you ever heard of “wardriving”? Wardriving is basically driving around town with a computer whose Wifi scanner is on. You combine that with GPS, so you know the strengths of various signals around your current location; this can be coupled with contextual information, such as stores or services nearby. Then you triangulate that information that so when you or someone else is in that area again, you can provide information on what’s nearby purely from Wifi signal. Both of these were fun projects and I got to work with some really smart people at the lab.

Did you learn how to write code during these projects?

I wrote very little code initially. I wasn’t a really good programmer at the time, and was not terribly attracted to coding, and for both projects I worked on the user side of the research, such as usability and user testing. I didn’t become interested in programming until a later experience in biomedical science where I saw code development as another tool to accomplishing my goals.

Later as an undergraduate, I interned at Seattle Biomedical Research Institute under Peter Myler. My lab worked on infectious diseases, and my first project was to build software to identify genes. This experience got me really interested in biology and research in general.

There’s a problem in biology which is pretty fundamental: you have a series of sequences, DNA, and want to identify the location of genes. At a simple level you can find stop codons, which are short sequences that suggest the end of a gene. One challenge is working out where these stop codons start, as they sometimes have many potential starting points. Over the course of a summer, I built software that used a combination of different methods to determine optimal starting position. I then used additional biological information specific to the species of parasitic genomes we were studying, to further enhance the technique.

Was that project the catalyst for you going to graduate school?

Yes, it’s also the project where I realized that coding wasn’t as bad as I thought, and began to appreciate the importance of computer science in modern biological research. At the time, all the computer science classes I took were taught in C, which is probably one reason I was a little turned off to the field; I wasn’t great at pointers or deallocating memory. But this was a great project because it had an application. I got to see what was going on, how it had an effect, and it made me interested in learning more about software engineering as applied to science.

I had a good understanding of the computational aspects because I’d encountered a project like that very early on.

How did you choose graduate school and also how did you choose what projects you wanted to work on?

I started with a Masters. I was very interested in just learning more about computing and biology, and I knew my school actually had a degree that was specific for this kind of focus so I opted to stay there. I went to the University of Washington for my Masters in Biomedical and Health Informatics.

My focus was actually just the next step in the procedure of finding the genes. Now that we’ve found the genes, can we make a best guess about what it is actually doing in the biological system it operates?

I used logic and data integration to annotate the genes; biology is full of databases that have information about genes. The problem is they’re so disconnected and fragmented that it’s difficult for someone to make sense of it. What we had was essentially a system for collecting this information wholesale and then federating them under some uniform schema. This schema says: “Here’s a gene. It translates to a protein. Here is some information associated with the gene.”

I worked on this with my advisor Peter Myler and the head of my department, Peter Tarczy-Hornoch. Essentially, our solution was to treat these sources as a large database. We mapped the information of data sources in an automatic fashion to the contents of the schema. Now you can start to ask things like, “What are the functions to which this gene maps?” We used logical inference to resolve these questions. Part of this was doing some shallow NLP, allowing us to parse the gene functions and other descriptors. It worked pretty well in comparison with human scientists doing manual annotation.

That was my Masters thesis. After that I wanted to work on something a little bit different for my PhD.

While there is a lot of biology in your research, there also seems to be a strong theme of building and engineering systems. Did you continue this intermixing of biology and engineering in your PhD?

While there was a heavy component of engineering, I wasn’t the only person working on the software platform on which my Masters project was built. There were a number of other folks in the lab that were working on variations of the same data integration methodology to solve different kinds of problems. In my PhD, I thought what I was doing with logic was great but there was something unsatisfying about doing something that’s a series of conditional rules. I wanted something more unified.

I started to read a lot about newer statistical methods. I thought we could apply some of them to federated data for protein characterization. Data integration generated a ton of information, and statistical techniques seemed to provide a more efficient way of making sense of that information without requiring curated logic. So that’s essentially what I did for my PhD. I took proteins and developed and applied a way of assigning function to them using data integration and statistical learning. Luckily, William Noble, one of the early researchers who helped pioneer machine learning techniques in biology was a professor at UW so I was able to get his help.

I focused primarily on pathogenic proteins; these are proteins in bacteria that tend to cause disease. An example would be one that facilitates the invasion of a bacterium into the host cell; another could be a protein that helps the bacteria attach to the host cell. All these functions were particularly critical for a consortium run by my advisor, the Seattle Structural Genomics Center for Infectious Disease. The Center’s mandate was to characterize and crystallize as many new proteins as possible from neglected pathogens.

The overall result was an approach that gathered heterogeneous and noisy data from myriad biological sources, unified them, and then used statistical methods to determine the likeliest protein functional class. We used the method that I developed to help prioritize and classify proteins for wet lab investigation. Even now, I will get an email from my old collaborators every so often saying, “One of those proteins that you selected in your system was just crystallized, it has a structure we’ve never seen before.” It’s wonderful and gratifying to see that my work is having a direct effect on the advancement of life science.

Graduate school was a really fulfilling time for me, because I was able to spend time exploring and found the specific niche in which I was really interested. If you have a good advisor and you have good support, it’s easy to do have this type of experience. The problem is that a lot of it depends on the luck of the draw. Did you pick the right advisor? Did you pick the right project? It’s especially true in the sciences where if you pick the wrong project, it might not bear fruit and you feel like you lost time. So I was lucky in the sense that I had great advisors and really great research projects to work on.

It seems like although you didn’t necessarily concentrate in CS in undergraduate, what you did for your master’s project and also your PhD was just as extensive of an education in data integration, software engineering and machine learning algorithms. How did you learn these topics without a background in them?

I think I was fortunate at the very least. Even though I did not start with a lot of hardcore programming skills, I did have a component of them from classes an undergrad.

But I think the biggest thing that contributed to my skill set was doing graduate school. Typically, graduate school is taking a few core classes followed by going deep into something you’re really interested in. As you go deep you are forced to learn the things you need to know along the way. So you end up taking extra classes, reading a lot, and meeting people who are experts in their fields because the goal is eventually to become an expert in your own field; you have to know quite a bit to advance science even just a little. At the time, as I learned more technical and analytical skills, it wasn’t learning just for learning sake, but as a means to an end. For me, this perspective made the learning much more interesting.

For example, one of the things I ended up doing as an aside with some colleagues was Natural Language Processing (NLP). We ended up organizing an NLP conference and workshop in my last year of graduate school. My role there was developing a quick software system for annotating medical notes used by workshop participants, and designing the statistical technique to evaluate results.

It was a competition. We had people from across the country submit their programs and their methods to pull out information from natural language text, which is actually pretty hard. Not only did they have to extract the medication, but they had to report the route and dose for the medication, all from transcribed medical narratives. This was a nice opportunity for me to work more on both my software skills and my statistical capabilities. These are the sorts of opportunities available in research, and especially in grad school, that helped hone my skills in research execution.

Did you also enroll in graduate coursework, or were you completely self-taught?

I took quite a few CS and other classes where there was some significant programming involved. Also, in my Masters program I worked a lot on a large code base. It was a fairly significant repo, with multiple people checking in/out code. So I had to really know my way around code and know that other people were going to be reading my work; I had to write decent comments and know what’s going on. Also, it was all in Java, which is a language that somewhat enforces structured overhead to begin with.

In addition, I worked very briefly for Cerner Corporation; they make one of the largest electronic medical record systems (EMR) in the US. I actually got to work on pretty cool R&D projects for their medical informatics group, and I had to keep the code well commented. Part of the exercise there was learning what is standard acceptable practice for software engineering. So that was a good opportunity to get an understanding of how engineering is done in a much larger ecosystem.

I think the nice thing about software development in general is that you don’t necessarily have to focus on it to pick it up. Reading is a pretty important component, both online and in books. There’s a canonical book on software engineering with regards to generating programming patterns. I read the whole book during the summer while I was working for that company. However, I don’t think there’s any better way than actually looking at other people’s code and writing code yourself. I had some really brilliant colleagues who wrote awesome code. So getting to see what they did and learning from them was a huge benefit.

We talked to several other people and it seems like your graduate experience was very extensive. Not only did you work on these two awesome projects but also you just found time to do extra bits.

I hardly slept in my last year! You realize when you’re in graduate school that as soon as you’re finished, it’s the real world. So I wanted to cram as much opportunity to learn as possible within the last couple of years there.

The other thing was that I got a scholarship from the Department of Defense to finish within a certain amount of time, because after that I’d get a job with the government as a civil servant. So if I didn’t graduate in time I’d get a penalty of more time in the government, which was not necessarily bad, but I wanted the option to leave whenever I wanted. My Masters was two years, a standard Masters. My PhD was about three and a half. When the US government can come after you for not finishing your degree when you said you would, that’s pretty good motivation to finish on time!

So immediately after graduating, did you have any thoughts about staying in academia?

Yes, I always considered it. But I had this obligation to the government to finish first. Because they paid for my last half year so I owed them the same amount in service.

One of the things that come up when people are thinking of leaving academia is that they feel isolated, whereas the draw of industry is that it’s intensely collaborative. What was your experience like?

A computational biologist will often work in conjunction with other scientists. If you think about a modern biological lab, you have a Principal Investigator, a number of technicians, wet lab scientists, people doing data management and then you might have a set of computational biologists. I think in modern biology you have a multidisciplinary team working on the same general problem where each person has their own task. One person designs experiments, another person does the data management. A different person follows up and sees if the results corroborate with models.

So in some sense it’s a squad. Each person has a specialized role and has ownership. It’s also very humbling because even for your small piece, you often realize there is something you didn’t take into account. That’s just biology: unless you have a gigantic memory capacity, you’re never going to commit the entire breadth of the field to recall.

After your stint with the government, what were your thoughts on what to do next?

One thing about science PhDs is typically you have to do a postdoctorate. I liked working for the government because of the emphasis on application; what I did there was being used to make decisions. So I wanted to find a postdoctorate that would give me that similar experience while still considering government as a field of work. I ended up coming over to Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in Livermore, California, to work as a postdoctoral scientist.

It was perfect because it gave me options. I could stay in government because it was still a government institution. However, it was also a postdoctorate so it meant I could go into academia afterward. Finally, it put me within striking distance of Silicon Valley. I felt it maximized my opportunities at the time.

After finishing your postdoctorate you had the chance then to look for academic positions, but also you were really close to Silicon Valley so there were a lot of startups and industry opportunities. So how did this influence your thought process?

I have to admit that I probably wasn’t as committed to doing academia at that point. I think if someone is so close to everything that’s going on in Silicon Valley you’d be remiss to not at least think about it. My postdoctorate was about to end, and the funding was lacking for this project. So there was uncertainty with regards to the likelihood of finding another project in my field there. Biodefense funding in government tends to come in waves of feast or famine.

I happened to be contacted by a recruiter out of the blue, who mentioned some mobile game companies that were really interested in finding someone to do data analysis and software engineering. So I thought, “I’m actually interested in biology and medicine, so if there’s anything there that would be a better fit.” She called me back later, tells me about this company, Ayasdi, and sent me a summary of what they were doing. It looked quite interesting, and ended up interviewing and joining. I think I was the 15th employee of the company.

And you’ve seen Ayasdi grow from a 15-person company to now many multiples larger. You’ve worked in many different settings, including very applied projects, that eventually led you to the exciting world of startups, although it was never your direct intention. Do you think yourself very fortunate?

Let me just step back a little bit. When you pick a major in undergraduate, part of that decision is thinking about what kind of job you want after you graduate. An important part of that question is: what are the skills that you want to pick up along the way? I don’t think graduate school is any different. I think one thing people in grad school have to be aware of is if they’re not fully committed to academia, you have to make sure that you’re building enough of a general skill set that you still have plenty of non-academic options open.

Take my grad work in data integration. I wouldn’t call myself a world expert in it, but I also know it’s a challenging problem that’s important for people to pick up and am fortunate to have gained valuable experience in it. In many cases, it’s a neglected area of expertise. So you want to be able to pick up things that you know are going to be useful.

Being able to pick that up and learn from smart people and get their advice was extremely valuable. Domain and skill don’t necessarily have to be completely intertwined. You can have a domain focus (in my case it’s biology and medicine), but you can still continuously pick up skills that are applicable to that domain but also have broad generalizability to others. I’m thinking about not just undergraduate but also graduate school going forward. Maybe you have a domain, but it’s important to understand that there are things that aren’t necessarily specific for that but are worth learning.

For me it’s been tremendously worthwhile. While developing the next iteration of Ayasdi’s software, we were at a little bit of a loss for how to figure out what to do with regards to the usability. I actually got to leverage undergraduate experience to help our team fix some of the early difficulties with usability.

Another example is just general analytical capabilities. The challenge in science is that statistics isn’t something with which many researchers are very adept. In many cases designing an experiment, even a computational experiment comparing methods, requires just basic statistics — enough that you can write a paper that confirms you’ve validated the results and you know that one method is likely better than others.

Also, I think breadth in our field is just as important in many ways as depth. Because if you’re touching all this data of various size and form, it’s important to have a good characterization of what you know and what you don’t know. The more broadly you have that, the better, but it’s also good if you have an area where you can go really deep. For me that’s biology and medicine.

So with all this in mind, when you joined Ayasdi, did you ever think, “Wow, this is really different from my previous roles”? And were there places where you thought, “Wow I’m really glad I had x, y, z experiences because this feels exactly the same”?

This is a very interesting position in the sense that a lot of it is actually working directly with people. If I look back at my background it’s mostly been head down working-on-numbers research. So having this component of it is quite unique for me. We are doing that heads down and work part, but there’s also a very significant part that involves working with new customers and understanding what their current challenge is, and how best to convey a solution. One of the biggest challenges I had to overcome was to suppress my introversion enough that I could speak without stumbling over my words. It was a big hurdle initially, but I’ve had plenty of practice now and eventually got comfortable with it.

Skill-wise, one of the key conditions when you’re looking at pharmaceutical data is that you have to be particularly rigorous about the statistics. This is a realm where we don’t necessarily want faster machine learning. We just want traditional, well-understood methods so that we know with some level of confidence that the results make sense. Fortunately, I’d had plenty of exposure during my graduate and undergraduate studies doing statistics and designing computational experiments.

A lot of emphasis is placed on the use of more advanced methods when in many cases having just a sound foundational understanding of basic statistics is more critical. It gives you grounding to look at an experimental design and understand at a very simple level why it was design in that way. Why are these the main effects? Why are they characterizing something this way? Why did they select these number of replicates? Using more exotic machine learning is great too and is often appropriate for contemporary data problems, but at the end of the day there are some really basic things that everyone has to know.

When we say data science, most people think about just data but less about science. A lot of people who do data science in industry start with the methods themselves and never really ask the questions such as: “What is causing the phenomena in the first place? How do I test that rigorously?”

I think one of the good things in biology is you’re forced to ask those questions. Typically, even simple methods can do quite well in biology under certain circumstances. I think in some sense what we have at this company is a fairly simple method, and I think that supervised methods typically are a great way to start and a great way to start to get into more detail. But, at the same time you just have to guard against this desire to go after the most interesting method when sometimes the simplest thing will give you the best and most explainable answer. As a scientist, I always want to be able to go back and understand the underlying principles. But if you’re looking at prediction, maybe that’s less important.

You’ve worked at Ayasdi for a few years now, but you’ve seen the injection of data science into the general vernacular of the technology companies. How do you make sense of what people are doing with the term “data science” today? How do you think Ayasdi fits into this ecosystem?

I didn’t even know this term existed until I got this position. I didn’t know data was a discipline of science. I thought it was a prerequisite for science, not a study unto itself. I’ve heard the definition, “It’s someone who’s better at coding than a statistician, and someone who’s better at statistics than a programmer.” In some ways you can turn it on its head: it’s someone who’s worse at coding than a software engineer but is worse at statistics than a statistician! I’m joking of course, but that’s how I feel about it sometimes since I’m well aware of my own shortcomings.

A lot of people that do this role have very interesting backgrounds. You don’t have a huge majority of people coming from a specific discipline; it’s mixed. When you look at something like computational biology, we’re used to dealing with messy, noisy, ill-formatted data. There are quite a few people who come from a biology background that do data analytics and data science. Maybe they picked up data wrangling skills along the way to do extract-transform-load.

The other component that is also pretty critical is some kind of statistical training. At the end of the day, the term data science means you’re a scientist, and you have an obligation to deliver results correctly. If you’re not happy with it you go back to the drawing board. There’s an important ability to understand and be able to evaluate whether or not what you’ve done makes sense from a statistical standpoint.

Then there is the domain expertise aspect. In many cases, we’re tackling problems that are fairly difficult and that require a lot of knowledge of a particular area. Moreover, being able to go to subject matter experts and speak the same language goes a long way to gaining credibility and trust from the person with whom you’re working.

I think many of the applied science areas of study, and certainly things that involve experimentation, are where many people get a lot of broad experience. Graduate school is great for giving you that deep domain knowledge and then hopefully along the way you’ve picked up sufficient amounts of statistics or mathematics to speak coherently about what you’ve generated, as well as the technical chops to execute.

Sometimes it’s just practice. For example, maybe you won’t know having certain data in a specific way is a problem, unless you’ve seen it before and have done the repetitions to deal with it in a very fast way. If you do this enough, even a massive data set can be turned over very quickly because you’ve seen it before and you know exactly what to do. In some sense a lot of it is as much pure practice as it is science.

You answered the first part of my question. The second part is: “How do you see data science in general?” Do you feel like Ayasdi is doing something different from the mobile apps companies? And if so, what is that special something?

When you look at what a lot of places are doing, it’s variations on the same theme. Which isn’t to say that’s bad or wrong; sometimes that’s what you have to do and there’s a big market in making that better and faster. In many cases there are tools and methods right off the shelf that one can adapt. Often, these were things that were developed just for those problems.

There’s been a big focus on supervised methods. However, as data grows, there are potentially many outcomes of interest — for some problems, we may have little idea of what to train for or what the expected outcomes even should be. It’s not that our current methods are deficient, but that with so much data, the number of potential questions with valuable answers grows very rapidly and cannot be enumerated by humans alone. Can we take advantage of very basic ideas in mathematics, such as distance metrics, and understand better where direct our attention?

What we do at Ayasdi is a very interesting way of looking at the large data problem. Our method applies well to high dimensional challenges or in many cases where people are completely inundated with data but have no idea where to search for potentially high impact discoveries. I can’t tell you how many times I’ve been in a meeting where someone says, “We have a lot of data, we know there’s something awesome in it that we can use to optimize our process/business/medicine/drug. But we don’t know where to start.”

Being able to elegantly and mathematically tackle this is going to be extremely useful as this becomes a very common problem. We’re already seeing this in many different business areas. Speaking just from my experience in biology and medicine, I see a lot of opportunity as more genomic and health information is collected and stored. There is a huge amount of value in just asking the right questions; the problem is that human ability to formulate reasonable hypotheses is finite and limited. So being able to identify and prioritize those questions in a data-driven way is going to be extremely important going forward.

What do you see coming out of the pipeline in the next three to five years in medicine and computational biology that you’re excited by, and that wouldn’t be possible without the new data tools and techniques being developed?

Medicine is a very interesting field. It’s a field where you need a lot of domain expertise to be really proficient. Take a physician for example who has to go through many years of school, sometimes more than a PhD, to be really good at what they do. How do they do that? They don’t do that by reading formulas or theorems. The biggest and most important component of their training is going to the hospital and seeing patients.

That’s how medicine is. But I think as we move forward it’s going to be critical to inject a lot of data there. To capture data, understand what’s going on, understanding how different practices affect results and outcomes. That’s not even touching the genomic aspect and personalized medicine. There’s so much information, there’s so much variability in how patients get treated across the board. How do we help make this more uniform?

Optimizing patient outcomes is a very interesting problem because it’s something that’s always been there and surprisingly, we do all these things with data but that’s still something that everyone wants to solve. I think that’s one area in medicine where where data science can help to make a positive and lasting impact.

I think that one of the things you mentioned very early on that doesn’t get talked about much is just how much work it takes to be really good at something. When you first started working, you worked very late into the night, most nights doing analysis. What drove you, and drives you as a data scientist today?

I think probably the biggest thing was curiosity. That’s actually a huge component. When I’m up late and trying to figure out a problem, my personal goal is to better understand what is driving whatever phenomena I am observing. I just want to find out. I’ve had this plenty of times here when working at Ayasdi, where I find myself facing a problem that is just driving me bonkers because I want to understand it better. Maybe I found this pattern and that pattern, and they all point to the same thing, but the outcome is the inverse of what I thought! So I want to dig deeper and know why. I think like any scientist the thing that drives me the most and really compels me to work late into the night until the sun comes up is curiosity.

If you could catch yourself in graduate school walking out of a lab at 3 a.m. and had a chance to speak to yourself, what would you have told yourself? How would you have lived life differently? Or would you have chosen anything different?

In terms of general direction, I probably wouldn’t change very much. I love biology and medicine, and the work is tremendously fulfilling. For the benefit of people who are interested in the field and doing data science as a career though, I would definitely say take as many statistics courses as possible. If anything, I would have told myself, “Hey! I know you don’t want to take that statistics genetics course because you have a completely full load, but take it anyways because you’ll end up using that information in your career at some point.” I end up having to look back at scattered notes or books because I didn’t take that statistical genetics course. Take more statistics courses, and take more math courses; though focus on statistics more than anything.

George Roumeliotis

Senior Data Scientist at Intuit

How to Develop Data Science Skills

George arrived on the fabled Stanford campus in the early 90s as a postdoc from Australia. After a couple of years doing research in theoretical and computational plasma astrophysics, the beating drum of the tech boom of 90s drew George into the unconstrained world of dotcom startups.

Undeterred by the Dot Com Crash, George went on to found JRG Software, which provided scheduling software for the food and beverage industry. His time as an entrepreneur proved to be an invaluable experience in making him a holistic Data Scientist.

When we interviewed George, he was a Senior Data Scientist & Data Innovation Leader at Intuit, a leading provider of personal finance and tax software. His interview touches on the minutiae of the hard technical skills, but also the macro and people skills which combine to make a holistic Data Scientist.

George has since taken a role as a Distinguished Data Scientist at Walmart.

Could you start off by telling us a little bit about yourself?

I’m originally from Australia, where I completed an undergraduate degree in applied mathematics at the University of Sydney, and began a Ph.D. in physics which I completed in the U.S. My focus was on theoretical and computational plasma astrophysics. More specifically, I investigated the physics of solar flares. I was a Senior Research Scientist at Stanford for several years before I realized that getting a tenured academic position was going to be difficult – there were so few spots in my sub-discipline. Around the same time, I started getting very interested in business applications of applied mathematics, and eventually I decided to make the leap out of academia and into business.

In the course of my research, I had developed Bayesian image processing techniques for astronomical images, which led me into machine learning, which in turn led me into online learning. Now, those were the days when everybody was starting a company, so I decided to join the party. I co-founded Dynaptics with a few business partners, raising about $5M. This start-up pioneered the development of adaptive learning systems to optimize online advertising. A non-technical marketing manager could “release” multiple advertisements into the system, and the system would learn in real-time which site visitor should be exposed to which advertisement in order to continuously optimize the revenue stream. As the site visitor behavior changed over time, the system would automatically adapt. Those were very exciting days, and our customers included MSN, eBay, and Cisco. Not so exciting was the Dot Com Crash in 2001, when the doors for additional funding slammed shut overnight. It was like nuclear winter for venture capital. We could not scale down our operations fast enough, so we had to shutter the company and sell off the technology and intellectual property.

Undeterred, I went on to found another start-up, JRG Software, with another set of business partners, this time raising about $10M. That start-up was in a completely different domain, namely factory scheduling for the food and beverage industry. The problem we solved was to enable factories to rapidly adapt to changing demand without holding a lot of inventory. One of our early customers was General Mills, which still uses our system to schedule all West Coast production of Cheerios! The business challenge was how to penetrate the headquarters of large companies like General Mills where SAP was firmly entrenched. We were eventually acquired by a public company that added our scheduling system to their product line.

At that point, my wife said something along the lines of, “Perhaps you should look at doing something other than a start-up next,” and I eventually arrived at Intuit as one of its first Data Scientists.

You were at Intuit before people started calling themselves data scientists, right?

That’s right. And it’s been a fascinating journey.

Along with the rest of the world, over the past five years Intuit has dramatically evolved its thinking regarding the applications of big data and advanced analytics. Five years ago, the focus was entirely on marketing optimization. Then, starting about three years ago, the scope increased to include improving the user experience by analyzing how users are interacting with our products. Now, the focus is squarely on leveraging big data and advanced analytics to create new products that solve important problems for our customers. Our unique aim is to deliver “Big Data for the Little Guy, which empowers individuals and small businesses by allowing them to benefit from the power of their own data as well as the collective wisdom of millions of fellow Intuit customers. This means that small businesses now have access to insights that were once only available to big, multi-million dollar companies, and enables consumers to put their own data back to work for them.

You worked at Intuit before there was a lot of hype and discussion about this term “data science”. As someone who’s been in this field for awhile, what are the myths and what are the truths when people talk about big data and data science?

You might have heard the joke, “What is a Data Scientist?” The punchline is, “A Data Scientist is a data analyst, who just happens to live in California.” I think the hype will go away, but Data Science will be a permanent feature of the business landscape. Data Science is its own unique discipline, combining elements of applied mathematics, computer science, business consulting, and, increasingly, new product development. I consider a good Data Scientist to be like a Swiss army knife, competent across all these areas, with deep expertise in one or two of them.

More specifically, the technical table stakes for a Data Scientist are advanced statistics, machine learning, SQL and Hadoop, and a mainstream programming language like Java. So there’s a combination of applied mathematics and computer science. But of equal importance are business consulting skills. These are often overlooked, or added as an afterthought, but they are critical. Business consulting skills can be the difference between a Data Scientist and a Data “Gopher”.

A Data Gopher is someone who responds to incoming requests for analyzing this or that, but who never has a seat at the table when the business decisions are being made. On the other hand, a Data Scientist with business consulting skills is like a senior McKinsey consultant, who can translate fluently between business and technical domains, and who is a trusted advisor to business leaders. Those are highly non-trivial skills.

When you talked about skills required in data science, you talked about three things: classical statistics or machine learning, computer science and business consulting skills. What suggestions would you make to someone looking to build those skills?

In terms of database skills, it is essential to feel completely comfortable with SQL and Hadoop. If you are still on campus, for goodness sakes take advantage of that by signing up for relevant basic courses that include a major project component.

In terms of programming skills, learning R is very important. It is kind of ugly, but it is the lingua franca. Personally, I would stay away from proprietary, commercial statistical programming languages. You know the ones I’m talking about. And certainly you need to learn a mainstream programming language like Java or C++. Learning a mainstream scripting language like Python or Perl also comes in handy.

If I had to assign a weight to help someone prioritize all this learning, it would look something like this:

SQL - 40%

Hadoop - 30%

R- 15%

Mainstream programming language - 10%

Mainstream scripting language - 5%

In terms of acquiring business skills, you have to get creative. At Stanford there was a fabulous entrepreneurship course tailored to engineers and scientists. Simply listening to lots of entrepreneurs tell their story is very helpful. Subscribe to The Harvard Business Review. Talk your way into a challenging internship that presents you with an open-ended problem. Above all, just start an online business. It doesn’t need to be the next Google. Give yourself the challenge of starting with $100 and seeing how much you can make it grow in a month. That can be quite eye-opening. Don’t become a Data Scientist who has never operated as much as a lemonade stand.

You have a very unconventional experience in that you left your postdoctorate position to found companies. Not only did transition from a postdoctorate to a business environment, but you jumped into the deep end and decided to start your own company. What types of thinking did you feel like you benefited from during your experience in academia and what are the things that you felt were hindrances to you when you entered the business world?

Having the foundation of applied mathematics was extremely useful, because then I could pick up other math-based bodies of knowledge very easily. On the Ph.D. side, I mainly learned persistence.

What certainly didn’t help me, and what I had to unlearn, was how academics present their results to others. As academics, we’re trained to take an axiomatic approach. *“Here at the start of the presentation are my axioms, and here in the middle are the detailed steps that I took, and then here at the very end are my results.” *But if you do that in a business meeting, and you hand out copies of your slides beforehand, you’ll observe that the first thing the business leaders do is flip to the back of the deck to see your conclusions. They just don’t care about the detailed reasoning, because that is your job, not theirs. I have found it much more effective to start with “the bottom line up front” and then show the thought process if there are questions. This is a very different mindset from academia.

Also, in academia you get kudos and endorphins from doing something novel. But in business it’s all about the efficiency with which the company can transform money into more money. So a Data Scientist needs to resist the impulse to solve problems ab initio, or to spend time going from the 80% percent solution to the 90% solution. That effort sometimes doesn’t make much business sense. You’ve got to think about allocating your time as though you were the owner of the business.

Intuit is a very data-centric and financial-centric company.You didn’t start out in a business context, so what framework do you use to evaluate the success of potential ideas at Intuit?

The way I look at business has definitely evolved, especially from being at Intuit. I’ve learned to take a hypothesis-driven, experimental approach to developing solutions to business problems. We should all feel passionate about the problems we are solving, but we must not fall in love with our solutions. We design experiments to let the customers choose between Solution A and Solution B, rather than that choice being made by “the loudest voice in the room.” That’s a mistake I made in start-ups, and one that I saw a lot of other people make as well. We were all convinced that of course we knew what the market wanted, and we proceeded to spend a lot of time building it. The way I work now, and the way I would have advised my younger self to work, is to create minimalist prototypes and test them out on real customers. Don’t fall in love with your own ideas. Market feedback is the only thing that matters. You’ve got to do experiments, and you’ve got to be ruthless about changing your ideas based on the results of those experiments.

We’ve interviewed people who have recently made the transition to data science, but as someone who’s seen the growth and development of younger data scientists, what are some of the mistakes often made by younger hires?

First, you have to proactively build relationships with your non-technical colleagues. Data Scientists are often by temperament introverts, but if you want to be effective and successful, you need to step outside that comfort zone. Email a non-technical colleague you’ve never met, and ask them to lunch. Make it your responsibility to form such relationships before you need them.

Next, practice viewing the world in terms of business processes. What’s a business process? It’s a foreign concept to many new Data Scientists coming directly from academia. A business process encompasses the people, systems and steps involved in a business activity. Generally speaking, a Data Science project has the goal of improving some existing business process. The truth is, it’s really difficult to change a business process.

For example, it took me a long time to grasp that improving the efficiency of a business process might actually be perceived as threatening to someone’s job, and the natural reaction of that person might be to consciously or unconsciously undermine any progress. So you have to develop deep empathy for the people involved in business processes, and create solutions that help those people transition to higher-value work. That sounds like a lot of responsibility for a Data Scientist, but if you don’t think about things like that, your ideas might never be implemented in the real world.

Beyond these three attributes, what does it take to be a successful data scientist, in your opinion?

A successful Data Scientist changes the world around them. It comes down to mindset. One mindset is that your responsibilities are to analyze a situation, construct a solution, and then pass along that solution to others for implementation. But that is a recipe for frustration for anyone who is interested in moving the needle in the real world. A better mindset is to think of yourself as the business owner who is responsible for changing how the business works. That’s a whole different mindset, one of taking ownership for how your ideas are going to be implemented and measured. The additional skill you need is influence without power. How do you influence others to move forward with your recommendations when they don’t report to you?

How do you influence others without power?

It is not easy, that’s for sure.

As I said earlier, it starts with being proactive in forming relationships with your non-technical colleagues, because people want to work with those they know and like.

It is also important to go for small wins before trying to hit the ball out of the park. Small wins prove that you are a reliable partner.

And you have to make the connection between your recommendations and the bottom line. Yes, that’s often very hard. There are usually many links in the chain between your work as a Data Scientist and the outcome for the business. But nobody else will do that analysis if you don’t. It goes back to having the mindset of the business owner.

When you’re looking for data scientists, do you feel there is a necessity for having any form of senior academic credentials? A lot of the data scientists we’re seeing now have a Ph.D. background, but do you think this trend will continue into the future?

Back in the day, when relational databases were brand new to the world, the folks who were most comfortable with that technology were at IBM Research. It is not surprising that the first relational database experts in industry had Ph.Ds, but over time the barrier to entry has obviously been reduced. Data Science might be like that. Maybe. On the other hand, Data Science might be more like brain surgery than SQL. I think it is too early to tell. The well-rounded Data Scientist is competent in applied mathematics, computer science and business. Such people don’t exactly grow on trees.

What distinguishes a data scientist from someone who works as a data analyst in a traditional business intelligence role, or a statistician with programming knowledge? How deep do these distinctions go?

Statisticians might be steeped in mathematical tools for inference and prediction, but that alone is not going to make them an effective Data Scientist. They also need to be completely self-sufficient in extracting and manipulating large data sets that are usually found in legacy systems, and which are often a noisy mess. They need SQL, NoSQL, and programming skills to do that. And even if they have all the programming skills, but they don’t have superb consultative skills, they will have very limited influence. I think a Data Scientist is a very different animal from a statistician. But that’s just my opinion. I’m not interested in getting into a religious argument about what constitutes a “real” Data Scientist.

You were the CTO of the first startup you founded and that seems to suggest that in addition to being an excellent physicist, you’re also quite skilled at building systems that provided software solutions built off your interests in image processing or scheduling. Were those programming skills something you picked up during the course of your graduate degree or was that more born out of need?

I found that software engineering courses at Stanford taught you how to write a program, but they did not necessarily teach you how to work in teams, or with diverse systems that you have to integrate. And they did not teach you how to build, deploy and maintain complex software. All that relates to project management and people skills which are usually not addressed in computer science programs. So I learned those skills via trial and error. Lots of error!

I acquired software engineering skills by actually building the Version 1 solutions at the two startups I co-founded. I think it’s very hard for Data Scientists to work effectively with software engineers if they haven’t done any software engineering themselves. I don’t think a Data Scientist necessarily needs to be a production software engineer, which is a different mindset yet again. But basic fluency – knowing how to write, document and test code, and how to create components that are used in larger systems, that’s important.

Where do you think data science is headed?

I think we are going to see an explosion of both consumer and enterprise products that are made possible by Data Science – that is, by the creative melding of big data and advanced analytics. To achieve that, some Data Scientists will need to become product designers, adding the skill of “design thinking” to their toolbox. Deep customer empathy, rapid iterative prototyping, and in-market experimentation will be essential to this emerging sub-type of Data Scientist. Or maybe we’ll need a new name. Data Product Designer, anyone?